Good morning.
Today's דף daf is
נ"ד. Nun Dalet. We're in the middle of the חזקה chazakah not
of three years, but the חזקה chazakah more related to מסכת קידושין
Masechet Kiddushin or the חזקה chazakah of taking possession, the specific act
that allows for a transfer of property. כסף, Kesef, שטר, Shtar, וחזקה.
u'Chazakah. חזקה Chazakah being an act that is the primary definition is
נעל, na'al, גדר, gadar, ופרץ. u'faratz. Basically, some, you either some type
of a thing that improves the land. Although we have seen in
a big חידוש chidush that the גמרא Gemara had yesterday was that
there is a form of it which is actually deriving benefit from
the land as long as it's direct. So sleeping, putting your sleeping
bag and sleeping on the land, that would be okay. But harvesting
fruit, that's not directly from the land, that's from the tree, and
that would not be. So the act that works for a חזקה
chazakah of ג' שנים, gimel shanim, which is the standard harvesting of
fruit, where your benefit comes later from the eating of the fruit,
that doesn't work. But it is an important חידוש chidush that the
גמרא Gemara just said, which is it's not just a mirror of
it, it's not just benefiting the land, there are cases of deriving
direct benefit. Okay, and now we pick up with the גמרא Gemara
on נ"ד Nun Dalet עמוד א', Amud Aleph, and we're just talking
also about like harvesting a palm tree and pruning a palm tree.
If it's done for the purpose, if it's evident that it's done
for the purpose of just getting the leaves or getting the branches
and not to improve the tree, it's not a חזקה. chazakah. Okay,
because then it is again not something that's been done to improve
the thing itself. That's just like that harvesting of fruit.
But if it's sort of cut pruning from both sides, so it's
reasonable to say that it was for the sake of the tree,
it does work. And that again also shows, by the way, that
the degree that intent can also be part of the act of
חזקה. chazakah. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: We're going
to have a string of statements similar to that. That was a
statement in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא Gemara takes
up ואמר שמואל, V'amar Shmuel, it is about eight lines down, beginning
of the line, four, five, six, seven, eight lines down. ואמר שמואל,
V'amar Shmuel, האי מאן דזכי זיחייא אדעתא דארעא, Hai man d'zachi zichaya
adaita d'ara, somebody who basically is cleaning up the land, taking away,
the רשב"ם Rashbam says that it means is that you are,
you're taking the weeds, you're pulling, you're picking up the twigs. Okay,
so I don't know, so you're cleaning up the land. So if
it is in order to improve the land,
so
אדעתא דארעא קני. adaita d'ara kanei. אדעתא דציבי, Adaita d'tzivi, if you
want the like twigs, okay, you're going to use the twigs for
like firewood or something, so לא קני, lo kanei, then it's not
good, then you're just taking twigs, you're not actually improving the land.
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, now how could you tell which is which?
שקל רברבי וזוטרי, Shakal ravrevi v'zutri, if you're taking both the big
twigs and the small ones, אדעתא דארעא, adaita d'ara, then you're trying
to clean the ground. שקל רברבי ושביק זוטרי, Shakal ravrevi v'shavik zutri,
if you take only the big ones and you leave the small
ones, אדעתא דציבי, adaita d'tzivi, then you just want the twigs for
firewood and therefore you're not bothering to take the small ones. Okay,
so very parallel to the discussion of the palm tree. ואמר שמואל,
V'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel also says another similar statement. האי מאן דאתקל
תקלא, Hai man d'atkil tikla, somebody that removes the stumbling blocks, like
somebody who removes the obstacles in the land. So basically you level
out the ground so there's no, there's no raised mounds, there's no,
there are no crevices or, there are no holes, you level it
out. So if it's אדעתא דארעא adaita d'ara to make the land
better so it can be plowed better, then קני, kanei, it works,
because you're improving the land. אדעתא דבי דרי, Adaita d'bei dari, if
however you're doing it for the sake of using the surface as
a threshing floor, לא קני, lo kanei, it's not good. Now that's
a little bizarre because if you're going to fix your land so
you can use the surface as a threshing floor, why should that
not be a way of fixing the land? Right? You've made the
land now usable in a particular way. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says
that it has to be in a context where you're doing it
only temporarily, that everybody understands that this land is here for plowing,
okay, and you are now, you need to do some threshing, you're
going to come in and level it and do some threshing, and
then you're going to leave after you do the threshing, and then
you'll want to go back and use it for plowing when the
season comes. So a temporary fix which is not really sort of
for the ongoing value of the land, okay, for the ongoing sort
of structure of the land, you know, it's just sort of like
you're moving in and doing this and then you're going to come
out, that's not considered a תיקון tikkun of the land, which is
still funny because you've anyway incidentally the land now has its, it's
not like you hurt it in terms of the other capacity. It
might be that the other capacity, the other capacity is not your
focus, but it didn't do something negative in terms of its ability
to be plowed.
I understand, I don't understand how it's a קילקול. kilkul. I mean,
that you're just that you're leveling it. Let's finish reading it, okay,
but that's the, then we have to look in the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
he says like this: So... If it's for using as a threshing
floor, then that's not the standard use of the land somehow. It's
only a temporary use, and therefore it's not a תיקון. tikun. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, amai, and how do you know? So
היכי דמי, heichi dami, שקיל מולייא ושדיא בנצחא, shakil mulya veshadya benatza,
if you take a mound and you throw it into a hole,
so you completely cause like a very flat leveling, אדעתא דארעא, adaata
de'ara, then that's for the sake of the land, that means that
you're going to use it for plowing, you want a totally level
surface. However, מולייא במולייא ונצחא בנצחא, mulya bemulya venatza benatza, a mound
in a mound and a hole in a hole, what the רשבם
Rashbam basically says means is it doesn't mean you create totally leveling.
You like smooth out the mound so they're not a big mound,
it's a smaller mound, or you level off the hole so it's
not a deep hole, but it's still a hole. In those types
of cases where you've like made it that there's not as big
mounds and as big holes but they're still not totally level, that
case is אדעתא דבי דרי. adaata debei daray. You don't, that's only
for a threshing floor because then you don't, for a threshing floor,
you don't need it to be as flat as you're going to
need it for plowing. So it's not a full enough תיקון tikun
for the plowing. So it's a little strange, right? Because okay, you
didn't make it totally flat. It certainly is not worse than it
was before. It's certainly better than it was before. You made it
flatter. So it's hard to understand something that even though it's only
temporary, but it actually is a somewhat improvement, why this would not
work even if your basic use of the land is for plowing?
Yes, Michal.
Do we know
from this land is plowing? Like sometimes flattening a land is not
for... right, so... say whatever, there's terraces for fruit.
Right, right. So that's what the רשבם Rashbam says, we have to
assume that context that it's plowing. He also goes on to say
that if actually it's clear that you want to use it ongoing
for threshing, then it would be a תיקון. tikun. So it's only
in a context where it's clear that your regular use is going
to be for plowing and that
this therefore is not what's needed. But absolutely, if the context was
different, something else would work. All right, so it's hard to understand
why this would not be a problem. Like Dove correctly says that
the רשבם Rashbam says, he says ונמצא שאין זה כאן כי אם
קלקול ואין זה מתקן. venimtza she'ein zeh kan ki im kilkul, ve'ein
zeh metaken.
So I'm not clear why is it a קלקול. kilkul. Maybe not,
maybe the flattening isn't a קלקול, kilkul, maybe the fact that you're
threshing it is maybe not as good for the ground for the
future when you're going to want to plow it. But it's hard
to exactly understand why there isn't a degree of תיקון tikun going
on here.
While it is not the center of the focus maybe?
You mean...
right, and you want basically a flat surface, but still the ground
is a flat surface is some type of a use of the
ground, like the ground for sleeping on, right, which we had the
other day.
Right,
you're don't, right, improving the land. Right. So and I think the
קלקול kilkul element maybe we have to assume that the act of
threshing and using the threshing probably isn't so good for the dirt
if
you're for the planting that you're going to want to be doing
later. Anyway, it's hard exactly to understand. תוספות Tosafot also was bothered.
It's interesting. I always like it when you get a little insight
into their actual concrete reality. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, he
says like this: מולייא במולייא, mulya bemulya, תוספות Tosafot says הקשה רב
יוסף מאורליינש, hiksha Rav Yosef de'Orleans, משמע שצריך קרקע שוה לחרישה יותר
מלידישה. mashma she'tzarich karka shaveh lacharisha yoter milidisha.
It sounds like you need flatter land for plowing than you do
for threshing. ואנן סהדי דלידישה צריך הרבה יותר שוה וחלק. ve'anan sahadi
delidisha tzarich harbeh yoter shaveh vechalak.
But in our experience is that for threshing the land has to
be much flatter than it has to be for plowing. So how
does this גמרא Gemara even make sense? Okay. ומה שפירשנו בקונטרס דאם
עשה אדעתא דגורן קבוע קני, uma she'peirashnam bekontres de'im asah adaata degaren
kavua, kani, if you're planning on making it a regular threshing floor,
קני, kani, that would work because then it's an improvement. היכי ידעינן
אי עביד אדעתא דגורן קבוע או אינו קבוע? heichi adinan iy avid
adaata degaren kavua o eino kavua? How would we know which one
it is, right? So it's too hard to measure. So therefore that
pushes for another interpretation of the גמרא. Gemara. והאי מפרש, ve'hai mefareish,
so רב יוסף מאורליינש Rav Yosef de'Orleans would explain the גמרא Gemara
דבי דרי דהכא, debei daray dehacha, when it says דבי דרי, debei
daray, it doesn't mean a threshing floor, which is what it usually
means. היינו להעמיד שם בהמות. hainu lehamid sham beheimot. What it really
means is that you want to actually use it for a barn.
Okay. כמו אבי דרי חושבנא דלקמן, kemo abei daray chushbana delakaman, תניא
דבהדר דבהמה לא קני. tna deba'hadar de'beheima lo kani.
That just having your animals on the land is not... now why
not? Why isn't that a use of the land? Why is that
different than having you sleep on the land or something? Or having
it actually that it's fixed enough to be used for that purpose?
So it's not exactly clear why that's different. But anyway, but at
least for him it allows him to explain that it's not really
this problem that for him threshing needs a flatter surface than plowing.
So how come this גמרא Gemara assumes that threshing doesn't need to
be as flat as plowing? And then he has רבינו תם השיב
לו, Rabbeinu Tam heishiv lo, שהם היו דשים במוריגים shehem hayu dashim
bemorigim ולא היו צריכים להשוות קרקע כל כך. velo hayu tzrichim lehashvot
karka kol kach.
Now what's a מוריגים? morigin? It's a, isn't that a, what is
that? That's like a type of,
not a plow... yeah, it's a tool, an implement. במורג חרוץ חדש
בעל פיפיות. bamorag charutz chadash ba'al pipiyot. It's a פסוק pasuk in
ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. It's some type of. and they didn't need the same
type of flat surface that we use because we use a different
technology than they did in order to do the threshing. So I
don't know exactly how the process was different, but I thought that
historical awareness was interesting. Don't start retrojecting our experience on the גמרא
Gemara and ask a question that we know we need a flatter
surface; they did it differently than we do. Yes?
What is threshing? Threshing is, I'm sorry, I didn't explain. You take
all of the wheat that has been harvested and everything is in
its husks, okay, and you have to get the kernels out of
the husks. So what you would do is you would take a
flat board that on the bottom side
would have spikes,
like in sneakers; they have cleats essentially, right, it has
spikes, and you put the wheat under it and the animals would
walk on the board and it would crush the wheat, and you
need flat ground because you have to and
then
you winnow it and you separate the husks chaff flies off? Exactly.
Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara.
It must be יוסי בר חאלין Yosei bar Chalin must be saying
that דגרי dagari is like the word deer.
Yeah, I guess, right, it's like a hundred. Right. That's a good
point. Right. Okay, ואמר שמואל, v'amar Shmuel, now Shmuel says similar issue
about how it all depends on context whether it's done for the
sake of the land or not. האי מאן דפתח מיא בארעא אדעתא
דארעא קני אדעתא דחיוורי לא קני. hai man d'pasach maya b'ara ada'ata
d'ara kani ada'ata d'chivri lo kani.
You basically are opening up water into the land, which it sounds
like it means you are diverting a stream, and the water of
a stream is going into a land. If you're doing it to
irrigate the land, that works, then you're doing something to improve the
land; that's a חזקה. chazaka. If you're doing it as a way
to catch the fish, okay, so then it doesn't work. Now how
do we know?
היכי דמי? heichi dami? פתח תרי בבי, pasach terei bavei, if you
opened up two openings, חד מעייל וחד מפיק, chad me'ayel v'chad mafik,
one brings the water in the land and the other brings the
water out of the land, so it just flows through the land,
so that's אדעתא דחיוורי, ada'ata d'chivri, then you're just trying to get
the fish to get caught in the land as the water's passing
through. פתח חד בבא, pasach chad bava, but if you only open
up one opening so the water comes in the land and stays
in, then you're trying to irrigate the land and that's אדעתא דארעא,
ada'ata d'ara, and then that is a חזקה chazaka because you're improving
the land. Okay, I assume again context would matter; sometimes you could
imagine you don't want the water to stay in the land, it'll
flood it, but anyway. Okay, ההיא איתתא, hahu itata, now there was
a woman what?
If you're growing rice, that's what you want to flood it.
Okay, ההיא איתתא דאכלה דיקלא בתפשיחא תליסר
שנין. hahu itata d'achla dikla b'tafsicha telisar shanin. So a woman was
eating a fruit of a palm tree or harvesting the branches of
a palm tree.
We had that word before at the top of the דף, daf,
if you remember, האי מאן דפשח, hai man d'pashach, a person that
prunes the palm tree. So she was basically pruning a palm tree
for thirteen years and taking the
fronds and the branches and benefiting from it, maybe taking also the
fruit. Okay, but remember, it only works an act that's not taking
the fruit from something but only basically that is improving the thing.
All
right, so אתא ההוא גברא ata hahu gavra and he dug a
little bit at the base of the tree. Okay, he turned over
a little bit of ground and improved the ground.
אזל לקמיה דלוי, azal l'kamei d'Levi, came in front of Levi, ואמרי
לקמיה דמר עוקבא, v'amrei l'kamei d'Mar Ukva, some say Mar Ukva, אוקמיה
בידיה, okmei b'yadei, awarded it to the guy who improved the ground
at the bottom. He says you have just been taking benefit from
the tree, you haven't been improving it. Okay, apparently it was not
the type of a pruning that was on both sides of the
tree that was for the sake of the tree; it was more
just harvesting the frond, and therefore that's not an improving of the
thing. Again, we did see that there are cases where you can
get benefit but it would be seen as a direct benefit. So
you know, like let's say somebody, I don't know, leaned against a
tree; that's an interesting question, like what would be comparable to the
sleeping on the ground? Let's say you scratched your back against the
tree, right, what is a but anyway, but that would be a
direct benefit. Cutting off the wood and then benefiting from the wood
at a later stage, that's not considered to be what? Hammock? A
hammock, right.
That's not considered to be benefiting the tree or getting direct benefit
from the tree as opposed to this guy that's improving the ground,
digging a little in the ground, so he did a
חזקה. chazaka. צווחה קמיה, tzavcha kamei,
so she yelled in front of him. אמר לה, amar lah, he
said to her, מאי אעביד ליך? mai avid lach? what do you
want me to do for you? דלא אחזיקת כדמחזיקי אינשי, d'lo achzikat
k'dmachziki inshi,
you did not do a חזקה chazaka like is the normal חזקה.
chazaka. Now that's a little funny because it's not like it sounds
like it goes by the norm of people, right, but it really
goes because of the Halacha that it's defined as giving benefit, not
deriving benefit. You know, so it's the phrase that we're looking at
is כדמחזקי אינשי, Kid'machzaki Inshi, which makes it sound like it's about
communal norms, right, is a little funny. Like, what could the communal
norms have been different that would have made a difference here?
That's exactly the tension here, but it's really fantastic. In other words,
she's she all along assumes that she was מחזיק Machzik the tree
because of what she's doing, because that's in the popular mind.
Yeah, but then he exactly said that's not what the normal people
do, right? So I don't exactly get it, meaning why is it
a function of what, you know... So now, maybe what it means
is, is that harvesting something is not... meaning all along what's the
idea of the חזקה Chazakah as a קנין? Kinyan? חזקה Chazakah is
a way of demonstrating ownership, right? So an owner, you know, I
assume that this is why normally, the normal difference, let's bracket the
discussion yesterday about sleeping on the land and deriving benefit. Let's go
back and focus on the idea that the primary חזקה Chazakah is
to give benefit. So you could say people who are not the
owner, right, like harvest the land, you know, take the fruit, like
if you're a sharecropper or whatever, you know, so but owner, the
owner is somebody who takes responsibility for something. He is the one
that really ensures, you know, that the land has a fence around
it, that it's watered, that it's whatever. So to some degree, I
am I am guessing that the reason let's just stop for a
minute and talk about that. Why is it that the חזקה Chazakah
of a קנין Kinyan is giving benefit to the land and the
חזקה Chazakah of three years is taking benefit from the land? Okay,
right, there's that basic difference. So I would say that the חזקה
Chazakah for three years is taking benefit because if you're on my
land and you're just improving it, I'm not going to protest. For
it to be a provocation for me to protest, you have to
be reaping the benefits. That's why the three years is taking benefit.
In terms of a חזקה Chazakah of ownership, why that primary one
is giving benefit, I would say because the primary act of being
an owner is taking responsibility for something, caring for something, not just
taking benefit from it. Okay? So that's what you could say is
כדמחזקי אינשי. Kid'machzaki Inshi. It doesn't mean you didn't do like other
people do when they want to do a קנין. Kinyan. What it
could mean is that this act is not an act that normally
shows ownership. An act that shows ownership is an act of taking
care of something, not taking benefit from something. So maybe that's to
some degree what is, you know, what this כדמחזקי אינשי Kid'machzaki Inshi
means. Anyway, so that's what he said. So אמר רב, Amar Rav,
so Rav says, הצד צורה Hatzad Tzura בנכסי הגר, B'nichsei HaGer, here's
another act of חזקה, Chazakah, somebody comes and draws a design on
the wall of a house of a גר, Ger, okay, בנכסי הגר
B'nichsei HaGer קנה, Kana, that's you're improving the structure. It now has
these nice designs on it, if you're a good enough artist, and
that's a קנין. Kinyan. דרב D'Rav לא קני Lo Kani לגינתא L'ginta
דבי רב D'bei Rav אלא בצורתה, Ela B'tzurata, because Rav only only
acquired there was a garden, a גינה, Gina, a garden near the
ישיבה Yeshiva of Rav, and apparently it was a נכסי הגר Nichsei
HaGer and it was owned by, you know, who died and then
it was הפקר, Hefker, and they and they made some nice, you
know, drawings on the walls of the garden and that was considered
a קנין, Kinyan, they improved it. So it's a little bit ironic,
you know, right after this whole thing with this poor woman who
for thirteen years has been harvesting this tree and it's oh, sorry,
you didn't do enough, and now we say, oh, but by the
way, if you draw a little picture, you know, that's enough. So
it's like this technical difference of taking benefit rather than giving benefit.
I just want to point out, so the רשב"ם Rashbam also, by
the way, just points out that if you might remember the גמרא
Gemara earlier spoke about plastering and drawing a picture, you know, doing
a ציור, Tziyur, and it said that it has to be an
אמה Amah long and it has to be opposite the opening, and
here it doesn't say that it has to have those criteria. So
he says, well, it depends. If it was just like normal like,
you know, curly-cues, like flowers, not not a big picture, then it
has to be on a more significant segment of the house. But
if it's a really nice picture, then it doesn't have to be,
then even a small section. I just want to read that and
then I'll take the question. If you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam,
he says,
בנכסי הגר, B'nichsei HaGer, it is seven lines from the bottom, בכותלי
הבית, B'kotlei HaBayit, אבל סיוד וכיור Aval Siyud V'chiyur דאמר לעיל D'amar
L'eil אמה כנגד הפתח, Amah K'neged HaPetach, that has to be an
אמה Amah long and it has to be opposite the doorway, לאו
היינו צורת בריה, Lav Heinu Tzurat Biryah, right, אלא ציורין בעלמא, Ela
Tziyurin B'alma,
מסתת צואים ופרחים. Mistat Tzo'im U'frachim. אבל צורת
חיה או עוף, Aval Tzurat Chaya O Of, but if you actually
make something that's like looks like representative of something, like like some
nice little pastoral scene, okay, חשובה Chashuva ודי באחד ולא בעינן אמה
ולא כנגד הפתח. V'dai B'echad V'lo Ba'inan Amah V'lo K'neged HaPetach. Different
degrees of how nice of your art, how good is your artistry.
It's like, you know, Picasso would go into a bar and he'd
get the you know he'd have these big bar tabs and instead
of paying his bar tab, he would take out a napkin and
he would draw a little picture and he'd sign his name and
he'd give it to the to the... so that would be a
much better than an אמה Amah ולאו סתם... V'lav Stam...
if the
guy held onto it, he was making a really good deal, yes.
What?
It's just funny because like a street artist coming forward and being
like, yeah, that graffiti on that wall, like...
That's my graffiti so it's my wall. Right. Yeah, right.
Okay, so all right, so now we have all this. Okay, so
now we have another question. איתמר *Itmar*. So now so again we
keep on switching back and forth between the act that's considered a
חזקה chazakah *chazakah* and the space on which it works. You might
remember before we talked about doing the חזקה chazakah *chazakah* on field
A doesn't work for field B if they're separated by a boundary
marker. So now we're going to have a similar type of a
discussion moving from the act to the area on which it works.
איתמר *Itmar*. שדה המסוימת במצריה *Sadeha mesuyemet bemetzareha*, a field that is
defined, it's sort of
designated, it's got the boundaries all around it, it's got boundary markers.
You know exactly
what the boundaries of the field are. אמר רב הונא Rav Huna
אמר רב Rav *Amar Rav Huna amar Rav*, כיון שהכיש בה מכה
אחת קנה כולה *Keivan shehikish bah maka achat kanah kulah*. So now
it's an interesting question. How much when you're doing the חזקה chazakah
*chazakah*, how does it relate to the entire field? I think all
along we've been assuming like this statement of רב Rav *Rav*. You
do one חזקה *chazakah* on a little piece of it and now
that it works, so the whole field, you've done a little thing
to improve the field. Okay, that's what רב Rav, *Rav* says. Yeah,
as long as the field is defined, you do a little thing,
it's a חזקה *chazakah* on the whole field. ושמואל אמר *Ushmuel amar*,
לא קנה אלא מקום מכושו בלבד *Lo kanah ela mekom makosho bilvad*.
No, I'm sorry, you know what you were קונה koneh *koneh*? That
exact area that you dug your hole or that you turned over
the dirt. Now, if that's true, why do we say if you
build a little if you build a fence or you make an
opening, it works for the whole field, right? If he says it
only works for the space. So it seems that the difference is
the following: a fence goes around the whole field, a wall goes
around the whole field. So improvement in the wall, building it up,
locking it, making an opening, is an improvement on the whole wall,
which defines the whole field. So that is something that goes that
relates to the whole field. Whereas if I turn over a little
piece of dirt, does that relate to the whole field or it
relates to this little section of the field?
Like building a house on the field, does that relate to the
whole field or just that area?
Just the area that the house is on? I don't know, maybe.
Could be. You're right, could be. Could be. We already learned that
a house without doors doesn't count. But it could be, you're right.
If so and so that's what שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* says. Until now
we've been talking if you think about it, the נעל גדר ופרץ
*Na'al gadar uparatz* are all things that are done on a fence
or a wall around a field, so that relates to a whole
field. What?
The woman's story.
Well, it seems like the dirt underneath the tree. Right, exactly. Exactly.
What?
Yeah, and this is making a distinction for שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* between
an ownerless field and a...
Oh right, so that's a good point too. Thank you very much
for pointing that out. Yes, so similarly to how we discussed yesterday,
remember if you're קונה koneh *koneh* field A you're not קונה koneh
*koneh* field B and we said that that would be different if
you actually were buying it. Because then the money defines both fields.
Or if we said somebody was gifting it to you possibly their
intent to give you both defines them as one unit. Remember that
discussion yesterday? Field A so right, thank you for mentioning that. The
same is true here. If somebody is selling it to you, their
intent, you know, if you can combine a field in New York
with a field in Miami, right, so you can also combine obviously
the whole field or the money that designates the whole field could
define the whole field. Thank you very much. So this would only
be a case when it's being קונה koneh *koneh* from הפקר hefker,
*hefker* where the act has to define itself. You don't have money
and you don't have somebody else's intent to define the scope of
the act.
Yes. Like if you pick up a corner of
a טלית *tallis* or even like a corner of
a... Right.
You pick up the whole thing though.
But you pick up a corner of it, you still... Right.
But even there there's an interesting discussion. Like when you do a
משיכה meshichah, *meshikhah* let's say you've got a big thing and I
do a משיכה meshichah. *meshikhah* like this. I don't completely displace it.
I move it an inch, but I haven't displaced it from a
certain place. So even though I haven't displaced it, I've moved everything
an inch. Right. So and let's say maybe it's true, maybe if
you pick up a טלית *tallis* and leave half of it on
the ground, maybe it doesn't work. Right. Maybe it doesn't work on
any of it. Right. Because you see the whole thing as an...
but the point is that there an object is a defined unit.
Ground, earth is not a defined unit. It's defined because of the
lines, but those but there's nothing physically about it that says where
does it begin and where does it end.
How are you going to you're going to dig a hole in
every single spot?
So we're going to see. Maybe you have to do something that
at least maybe goes the fullness of one of the dimensions. Okay?
Maybe, you know, you could say you have to go both the
length and the width. Maybe you have to dig a furrow, the
length... but we'll see, it's coming up.
That would be the image of אברהם Avraham אבינו *Avraham Avinu*.
Right. לארכה ולרחבה *Le'orkhah ulerakhbah*. לארכה ולרחבה *Le'orkhah ulerakhbah*, yeah, that's a
very good point.
Very interesting image. Right. You're going to be קונה koneh *koneh* the
land, you
got to walk the whole thing. Right. To define the whole thing.
Thank you, that's a good image. Right. So let's just turn the
דף *daf* and see what it is. ושאינה מסוימת במצריה *Veshe'einah mesuyemet
bemetzareha* now. According to שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* we don't know for שמואל
Shmuel *Shmuel* what would I have to do to be קונה koneh?
*koneh* the whole land, right, if I was doing it through digging
and not building a wall and again the case which is הפקר
hefker, *hefker* which you don't have somebody else defining the whole thing
as one unit. We don't know according to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. But
even within רב Rav *Rav* we can ask... So if the boundary
markers aren't there, so if the boundary markers aren't there to define
the the you know the identity the boundaries of this piece of
this plot, how does your when how would your קניין kinyan affect
like the whole space? So עד כמה, ad kamah, so until how
much? So אמר רב פפה amar Rav Pappa כי דאזל טיארא דשורי
והדר, ki de'azal tayara deshurei vehadar, like basically like a team of
oxen will go plowing the land, go one direction and come back.
Now, what does this mean how much? So there is a debate
here between the רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות. Tosfos. The רשב"ם Rashbam says
it means
how much do you need to do to be קונה koneh the
whole plot if it's not if it doesn't have markers? And what
do you have to do to be קונה koneh the whole plot
is you have to go right back and forth one dimension. So
even though you're only going the width and you haven't defined the
length, I mean people do know, you can go look up the
deed, you can see what the length is. It's just not physically
defined. So if you want to be קונה koneh the whole plot
according to רב and maybe according to שמואל Shmuel even when there
are markers, you have to go one dimension back and forth. That's
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it. תוספות Tosfos says that's not
what the גמרא Gemara is saying. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say how
much do you have to do to be קונה koneh all of
it. What the גמרא Gemara is saying is is that when you
just dig one hole, if there are no boundaries, how much are
you קונה with one hole? Okay, right? Remember that was the scenario.
You dug a hole, שמואל Shmuel. says you just get the hole
and רב says you get the whole field when there are boundaries.
When there aren't boundaries and you dug one hole, how much are
you קונה? That's what תוספות Tosfos says. And the answer is like
one you know two you know two furrow length, you know, back
and forth. Okay, so still according though to תוספות, Tosfos, the question
is okay, but let's still ask that question. How much would you
have to do if it did not have boundaries to be קונה
the whole field? Right? So תוספות Tosfos says he basically more or
less agrees to the רשב"ם. Rashbam. He says all right, I agree
you'd have to go one length. You wouldn't have to go back
and forth, you'd have to go one length. But basically רשב"ם Rashbam
and תוספות Tosfos basically agree that if there are no boundaries or
one could imagine the same would be true according to שמואל, Shmuel
you go one dimension maybe back and forth or just one dimension
and that designates that it's an act done to the whole plot.
One little hole is just done to that space. One whole dimension
designates it being done to the whole spot. But yeah, you could
have logically said you have to go you know both dimensions, length
and width. Okay, so that's that's that's that question about how to
define the act that connects to the whole space, certainly and when
we are talking about הפקר, you know, where you don't have the
money or you don't have the דעת da'at to designate the whole
space. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר שמואל. amar
Shmuel. So now we're going to switch gears to a different to
a different discussion which is not about the act of חזקה per
se, it's about it's about taking possession of land, but it actually
gets into a very important this is one very central גמרא Gemara
within the discussions of the principle of דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina demalchusa
dina. So it's something we wouldn't have been expecting from the conversations
we've been having, but we're now going to open a really new
conversation. Let's take a look. Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel נכסי עובדי כוכבים הרי הן כמדבר.
nichsei ovdei chochavim harei hen kemidbar. The property of non-Jews is like
the desert, is like ownerless property or the wilderness. כל המחזיק בהן
זכה בהן. kol hamachzik bahen zachah bahen. It's a free-for-all. Anybody who
takes possession takes
you know anybody who does a חזקה on them takes possession of
them. Now really what does that mean? It means I can just
go to my next-door neighbor the non-Jew and do a חזקה on
his house? So no, it means as we're going to see when
they are in the process of being transferred,
you can jump in and seize them. What's the case? מאי טעמא?
mai ta'ama? עובדי כוכבים מכי מטו זוזי לידיה אסתלק ליה. ovdei chochavim
miki matu zuzai lideih istalak leih.
So the קניין kinyan of when you buy land from a non-Jew,
the what affects the transfer is the paying of money because basically
there's an interesting debate you might remember in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
whether the standard קניינים kinyanim assumes that the standard קניינים kinyanim of
Jews and of non-Jews
are like you know are not the same, are they are the
opposite of one another. So if the standard קניין kinyan that a
Jew does by chattel by by is משיכה, meshichah is like physically
taking possession, then the standard קניין kinyan of a non-Jew would be
by money. Or the reverse, if the standard קניין kinyan of a
Jew is by money, the standard קניין of a non-Jew is like
by משיכה. meshichah. So רשב"ם Rashbam says we're here assuming that all
the קניינים kinyanim of non-Jews are by money, okay, even though by
Jews it might be by משיכה or other types of things. תוספות
Tosfos says well, not all קניינים, kinyanim, maybe by actually chattel maybe
non-Jews is by משיכה. But at least by קרקע, karka, תוספות Tosfos
says, and his proof is where is a case in the Torah
that we have a non-Jew קרקע karka with money?
מערת המכפלה, Mearas Hamachpelah, עפרון. Efron. So that's what תוספות Tosfos says.
So there we see that whatever the general rule of how a
non-Jew takes possession of things, we know that when it comes to
קרקע, karka, it's through money. Okay? So you give money to the
non-Jew, that should affect the transfer. Okay, but here's the point. If
you're in a place where as we've as I've mentioned before, although
כסף kessef works for Jews as well by קרקע. karka. The standard
of most places was you would not let it be done just
by money alone, you would insist on a שטר shtar because right,
you really want to make sure you've got that deed. That's really
critical, you know. So therefore it's a place where they standard write
a שטר, shtar, כסף kesef doesn't do it alone, you also need
a שטר. shtar. So apparently that idea that we're in a place
that writes a שטר shtar and therefore שטר shtar is part of
the process is- six, you know, sort of is relevant for the
Jew to take possession. You don't yet take possession if you're buying
from a non-Jew until you have a שטר shtar because you know
in your- because that's the standard that a שטר shtar would be
written and so therefore but he he's not buying into that whole
way of thinking. For him, as soon as he gets the money,
he's out of the picture. So he's out of the picture once
he gets the money, you haven't taken possession until the שטר shtar
is written. So right now this land is ownerless. His ownership has
ended and yours hasn't yet begun. And some third party can come
in and snatch the land from under you. Let's just read this.
Okay? He says איהו כחזא מחמת זוזי לידיה אסתלק ליה, avehu kechaza
mechimat zuzai leyadei istallik lei, he removes himself because for him כסף
kesef was enough. ישראל לא קנה עד דמטי שטרא לידיה Yisrael lo
kanei ad demati shtar leyadei and the Jew doesn't take possession if
it's a non-Jew selling to a Jew because the laws of for
Jews is that in if this is the standard in this locale
between Jews that you need a שטר, shtar, that would be relevant
even when buying from a non-Jew.
הלכך hilkach and therefore he hasn't taken possession yet. הרי הן כמדבר,
harei hein kemidbar, that right now ownerless. וכל המחזיק בהן זכה בהן.
v'chol hamachzik bahem zachavah. Anybody who grabs it takes possession of it.
Okay now by the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says points out that
might be legally correct, but it's still a pretty immoral thing to
do. Like this guy paid money and now you're taking it from
under you know from under this guy's nose. Okay so I'll get
back to that in a minute but Jenna you had a question.
Okay? So let's explore two things here. First of all
תוספות Tosfos asks a very reasonable question. תוספות Tosfos says look
since כסף kesef can work for Jews as well and it only
doesn't work because the standard, the norm, is to write a שטר,
shtar, I would think that when you're buying it from a non-Jew
no person wants this property to exist in this no-man's land in
the middle of the transaction. So in that context if the non-Jew's
ownership ends with כסף kesef presumably the default assumption would be that
you would be קונה with כסף. kesef. Right, it wouldn't be a
case if you're buying from another Jew and everybody always assumes שטר
shtar gets written you'll say the whole transaction doesn't take effect until
a שטר shtar is written. But in this case where half of
the transaction is taking effect with כסף kesef you would assume you
would want your half to take effect with כסף kesef as well.
So how can you- how can this work? Like how can it
be that you need a שטר? shtar? So if you take a
look תוספות- Tosfos I mean it's an excellent question, you'll see if
you like the answer or not. Okay so תוספות Tosfos says look
at
תוספות: Tosfos: ישראל לא קנה עד דמטי שטרא לידיה, Yisrael lo kanei
ad demati shtar leyadei, שהיו עומדים במקום שכותבין את השטר. shehayu omdim
bemakom shekotvin es hashtar. It would be a default to write a
שטר shtar and therefore that would be necessary.
וקשיא לרבנו שמשון מאנברא דאמאי לא קני בכסף גרע מעפרון. Vekashya lerabeinu
Shimshon me'Anvra d'amai lo kanei bekesef gera me'Efron. So first of all
you have the עפרון Efron where אברהם Avraham was קונה with כסף.
kesef. The same way עפרון Efron stopped owning it,
אברהם started buying it. בקל וחומר מגופו ואחז ממונו בשתים Bekal vachomer
migufo v'achaz mamono bishnayim etc. וליכא למימר שאינו גומר בדעתו
לקנות עד שיהא בשטר. Uleka lemeimar she'eino gomer beda'ato liknot ad sheyehei
beshtar. You can't say that oh no no the Jew hasn't fully
committed to buying it until he gets a
שטר. shtar. דאחר דעובד כוכבים מסתלק De'achar d'akum mistalek once the non-Jew
stops owning it of course he wants to get it at that
moment. והיאך ויהיב הממונא v'heich veyahiv hamamona למה לא יגמור בדעתו לקנות
יניחנו להיות הפקר? lamma lo yigmor beda'ato liknot yanichenu liyot hefker? He
should rather leave it right to be ownerless? דהוה ליה למימר כאילו
פירש אי בעינא בכסף קני. Dehava lei lemeimar ke'ilu peireish ibaeina bekesef
kani. Like I
I want to be able to possess it just with money. Okay.
וצריך לומר דאנן סהדי שלא היה בדעתו אלא כמו שהוא רגיל לקנות
מישראל דהיינו בשטר אע"ג דלא פירש. V'tzarich lomar d'ana sahadi shelo haya
beda'ato ela kemoshehu ragil liknot miYisrael dehainu beshtar amilo peireish.
So the question is much better than the answer. The answer is
look since whenever you buy from a Jew it's never complete until
there's a שטר shtar even when you're buying from a non-Jew we
assume you're working with the same parameters that you don't want the
deal to be complete even with a שטר. shtar. So even though
it can in principle work with כסף kesef and that'll protect you
from some third party coming in and grabbing it nevertheless your expectations
and assumptions are that you're not going to be קונה without a
שטר. shtar. So we have this gap where he stops owning it
when he gets the money and because the way you normally operate
with Jews is it's not final until a שטר shtar those are
your assumptions here as well and it remains ownerless in the interim.
So one more- one more other thing. So now the question though
is what about this nasty guy or this you know
who comes in and he grabs it? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says
well that guy's called a רשע. rasha. Anyway because there's a גמרא
Gemara that says עני המהפך בחררה ובא אחר ונטלה הימנו. Ani hamahapech
becharara uvah acheir vinetalah heimenu. There's a poor person he found some
piece of food on the ground and he's clearly he's about to
take possession of it. He technically hasn't done a מעשה קניין ma'aseh
kinyan and you run up and you grab it from him. It
says that you're called a רשע. rasha. So he says here too
you're called a רשע. rasha. Now that's all very nice, but then
why didn't we say that by the way before about that guy
that snatched the palm tree from that poor woman who had, you
know, for thirteen years benefiting from it? Maybe we would say, maybe
that's also a רשע, rasha, okay? This clear one person is trying
to possess and you're snatching it. But here it's even worse because
here I paid money to the non-Jew. You're going to take it
from me? What am I going to do, ask the non-Jew for
my money back? He's going to laugh in my face. So can
I ask you for money? You took it. And the רשב"ם Rashbam
says no, the גמרא Gemara sounds like the third party gets it
and he doesn't have to reimburse. You know? So it's really, it's
a real רשע. rasha. You took the field away from me, and
I'm not just didn't get a מציאה, metzia, didn't get something from
הפקר, I'm actually out the money that I paid. And תוספות Tosafot
has a whole question about is it possible that I can get
compensation from you or not? But obviously it's a pretty nasty thing
that you just did to me. Okay, but technically the land can
exist in this no man's land. So let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes with it. Okay.
So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said to him
to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, מי אמר שמואל הכי, mi amar Shmuel
hachi, how could שמואל Shmuel, ever really have said that? ואמר שמואל
דינא דמלכותא דינא. ve'amar Shmuel dina d'malchusa dina. שמואל Shmuel is the
author of this famous statement that the law of the king is
the law. Okay, so therefore we go by, you know, the secular
law in the in the country in which we live. ומלכא אמר
umalkah amar and the king has said לא תקני ארעא אלא באיגרתא,
lo tikni ara ela be'igarta, that the land doesn't transfer except with
a שטר. shtar. So therefore the same way we only קנו kanu
with a שטר, shtar, the non-Jew only is out of the picture
with a שטר. shtar. It might be that we say, oh, according
to הלכה halacha the non-Jew is out of the picture as soon
as he gets the money. It's all very nice according to הלכה,
halacha, but according to the secular law, the non-Jew only transfers with
a שטר. shtar. So therefore nobody, you know, so it doesn't live
in this no man's land. Without a שטר, shtar, nothing has happened
yet according to secular law. So here's a great question: when you
have a financial transaction, do you apply, you know, הלכה halacha or
do you apply secular law? And it's saying according to שמואל Shmuel
we should be applying secular law. Alright. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
אנא לא ידענא, ana lo yadana, I don't know how to resolve
those two statements of שמואל. Shmuel. But here's how I know that
that's what שמואל Shmuel said. באובדא דהוה בדורא דרעותא, be'uvda d'hava beDura
diReusa, there was a case in this place דורא דרעותא, Dura diReusa,
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it's a name of a place or it's
a village of shepherds, okay, like a רעיא raya is a shepherd.
בישראל דזבין ארעא מעובד כוכבים, beYisrael d'zavin ara me'ovad kochavim, a Jew
bought land from a non-Jew. ואתא ישראל אחרינא, va'ata Yisrael achrina, and
another Jew came, רפיק בפורתא, rafik bepurtah, turned over a little bit
of the land. אתא לקמיה דרב יהודה, ata lekamei deRav Yehuda, and
came in front of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. ואוקמה בידיה, ve'ukmah b'yadei,
so, and he said the guy who turned over the land now
owns it. And רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was a תלמיד talmid of
שמואל, Shmuel and we should assume that this is a פסק psak
based on שמואל's Shmuel, teaching. Okay, בידיה דשני, b'yadei deshaini,
let the second guy who jumped in keep it. So that's how
I know that the same שמואל Shmuel, who says דינא דמלכותא דינא
dina d'malchusa dina said that you can jump in and seize this
land. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so אביי Abaye said back to
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, דורא דרעותא קאמרת? Dura diReusa kamart?
You want to bring a proof from that story of that village
of shepherds? התם באגי דמטמרי הוו. hasam bagei d'mitmari havai.
There they were like
swamps that were being, meaning plots of land that were being hidden
away from the government. Basically, people were in arrears for back taxes
on the land. Okay, and that was the land that was being
sort of sold and transferred where the people were in arrears for
the real estate taxes. דאינהו גופייהו לא הוו יהבי טסקא למלכא. de'inhu
gufaiyu lo havai yahavi taska lemalchah.
They themselves were not paying, the original non-Jewish owner of the land
had not been paying the taxes to the king. ומלכא אמר umalkah
amar and following the principle of דינא דמלכותא, dina d'malchusa, right, because
אביי Abaye is the one who is saying we need to go
by דינא דמלכותא, dina d'malchusa, the king has said, ומלכא אמר, umalkah
amar, מאן דיהיב טסקא לכול ארעא. man d'yahiv taska lachol ara. The
person who's willing to pay the back taxes can get the land.
Okay, so therefore apparently the way he's claiming the story happened is,
the non-Jew, the reason the second guy was able to take the
land was because the second guy seized the land and paid for
the back taxes to the government. We weren't told that part of
the story.
Distressed lands in default.
Exactly. So it's saying that's not because of this idea that the
non-Jew was removed and the Jew hadn't seized it yet and a
third guy seized it. That's not, no no no. It's all דינא
דמלכותא. dina d'malchusa. So דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchusa was that the reason
דינא דמלכותא dina d'malchusa works is because the second guy, the second
Jew was entitled to take it because he was the guy who
paid the back taxes to the king. You totally misunderstood the case.
Okay, so we still don't know though how to resolve it with
the two statements of שמואל. Shmuel On the one hand שמואל Shmuel
says דינא דמלכותא דינא dina d'malchusa dina and therefore it should all
go by the secular law, and on the other hand we have
this idea that it's like, at least the claim of רב יוסף
Rav Yosef is that some third party can come in and seize
the land. So let's read one other story and then I'll say
something about that. Okay, it's a nice little story here.
Okay, רב הונא זבין ארעא מעובד כוכבים. Rav Huna zavin ara me'ovad
kochavim. So we have a case just like this. רב הונא Rav
Huna bought a plot of land from a non-Jew. אתא ישראל אחר,
ata Yisrael acher, some other Jew came, רפיק בפורתא, rafik bepurtah, turned
over a little bit of the land, אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן, ata
lekamei deRav Nachman, came to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. רב נחמן ואוקמה
בידיה, Rav Nachman ukmeiviyadei, said okay, we're going to award it to
this guy who jumped in. Okay, same by golly, assuming again, not
dealing with the דינא דמלכותא dina demalchusa question, assuming this idea is
true that there's this gap of ownership between the non-Jew leaving and
the Jew taking possession that lets a third party come in and
seize it. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
to... I'm sorry, רב הונא Rav Huna said to רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, מאי דעתך, mai daitach, why are you פוסקנ'ן paskining this way,
taking it away from me? דאמר שמואל נכסי עובד כוכבים הרי הן
כמדבר וכל המחזיק בהן זכה, da'amar Shmuel nichsei oveid kochavim harei hen
kemidbar vechol hamachzik bahen zach, because of this teaching of שמואל Shmuel
that when it's in the middle of being transferred, a third party
can seize it. That's why you, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, are פוסקנ'ן
paskining that this guy gets the whole plot of land, he came
in and he seized it? Okay, as long as we're going like
שמואל, Shmuel's let's be consistent.
ליהוי לי מר כאידך דשמואל, leivei li mar ke'idach deShmuel, פוסק paskin
like the other פסק psak of שמואל, Shmuel? דאמר שמואל לא קנה
אלא מקום מכוּשוֹ בלבד. da'amar Shmuel lo kana ela makom makosho bilvad.
Oh, now we see how it's tied in because we learned at
the beginning of today that שמואל Shmuel says let him get the
place where he dug, his shovel gets a hole and I'll still
get the rest of the land. Fine, you want to פוסק paskin
like this crazy idea of שמואל that the guy can come in
and seize it? Good. But let him just get his little hole.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said no, you know what, בהא אנא
כשמעתך סבירא לי, baha ana kishmai'atich svira li, I, there I go
like, you know, like my, like my teaching, דאמר רב הונא אמר
רב, da'amar Rav Huna amar Rav, because I've taught... I taught...
כשמעתך, kishmaitach, it should be סבירא לי. svira li. There I go
like how you פוסק paskin because רב הונא Rav Huna here was
the guy was trying to buy the land. You right, רב הונא
Rav Huna, in front of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. You, רב הונא,
should be כשמעתך. kishmaitach. דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, da'amar Rav Huna
amar Rav, says you yourself say in the name of רב, כיון
שניכש במקום אחד קנה כולה. kivan shenikesh bemakom echad kana kulah.
So so here I'll be very nice, I'll פוסק paskin like you,
so you lose out both ways. I'm going to פוסק paskin like
שמואל that a guy can jump in, and I'm going to פוסק
paskin like your teaching in the name of רב that one little
shovel you get the whole land. Now let's talk for a moment
about this idea of how do you reconcile this with שמואל teaching.
What?
Why would you want to do all that? Right?
I mean, it's crazy that you would want to to leave that
like opening there for somebody to come seize it. So let's actually
talk about that, about this issue of דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina demalchusa
dina. Okay, so first of all, why is it that דינא דמלכותא
דינא dina demalchusa dina would not be relevant here? How do you
reconcile שמואל? The גמרא Gemara never reconciled it. So you know so
the רשב"ם Rashbam says a very unsatisfactory answer to this question. The
רשב"ם Rashbam's answer is it must be that that wasn't what the
law was. The law wasn't that you need a שטר. shtar. You
know, so yes we go by דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina demalchusa dina,
but you don't need a שטר. shtar. That's not, you know, people
he misunderstood what the actual secular law was, which is a little
hard to believe that they're debating about what actually the secular law
was. That's not a very satisfying resolution of it. Assuming the secular
law is that you need a שטר, shtar, right, how do you
reconcile them? So another way of dealing with it... this really is
a very rich גמרא Gemara because the issue that all the פוסקים
poskim have to deal with with דינא דמלכותא דינא dina demalchusa dina
is what is the limit of that? How much is secular law
going to override הלכה? halacha? Right? I mean you can't let secular...
now like for example would we say that you go by secular
law and you don't need a גט get because as long as
you get a divorce like that you know obviously it's not going
to compromise you know sort of like what we say like ritual
law? Okay but how much will it have an impact even in
דיני ממונות? dinei mamonos? Right? Let's say for example how about laws
of inheritance? Would you say you will ignore the תורה Torah's laws
of inheritance and you go by the secular laws' definitions of inheritance?
So the ראשונים Rishonim were very clear that that's not true. The
רמב"ם Rambam says absolutely not, it says by the laws of inheritance
it says חוק כתיב ביה, chok kesiv bei, it's not like a
normal question of just דיני ממונות. dinei mamonos. You could say because
there it's not a transaction between two people, it's something that happens
automatically. But it becomes this real profound question of like how much
are we just going to get rid of our הלכה? halacha? Like
and the רשב"ם... Rashbam... the רשב"א Rashba actually has a whole תשובה
tshuva where he discusses this. He says you know somebody asked him
well in this case should we say דינא דמלכותא דינא? dina demalchusa
dina? So the רשב"א Rashba says says yeah you know what? The
רשב"א Rashba says why don't we just stop teaching everybody all of
נזיקין, Nezikin, throw out all of חושן משפט? Choshen Mishpat? חושן משפט
Choshen Mishpat didn't exist then it wasn't a שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch.
But he says who needs who needs all of the books of
רבינא ורב אשי? Ravina veRav Ashi? Let's just learn secular law and
why don't we you know... so of course you can't say that
we go by דינא דמלכותא dina demalchusa to override all of דיני
ממונות dinei mamonos cause then what's the whole point of you know
of a quarter of ש"ס Shas that's on you know that's on
דיני ממונות? dinei mamonos? Now the irony is of course that in
a lot of contemporary cases in בית דין beis din and בתי
דינים batei dinim nowadays a lot most of their decisions are not
based on חושן משפט, Choshen Mishpat, are not based on like technical
הלכה. halacha. A lot of it is based on דינא דמלכותא דינא,
dina demalchusa dina, like I think like 90 percent of their decisions
are based on some combination of דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina demalchusa dina,
compromise and like and equity you know considerations. But anyway but the
רשב"א Rashba takes like profound offense. How can you think that we
should just override all of דיני ממונות? dinei mamonos? So the question
is well what are the parameters of it? When do you know...
if you so there's one opinion that basically says you only would
apply it in cases where like like הלכה halacha doesn't say something
about it, like there's like a gap in הלכה. halacha. הלכה Halacha
doesn't address a case. Like an interesting example would be let's say...
For example,
intellectual property. There's no idea in הלכה Halacha about intellectual property. So
there we would go by דינא דמלכותא דינא. Dina D'Malchusa Dina. Now
a counterargument could be, if there's no idea in הלכה Halacha about
intellectual property, then that means that there is no intellectual property in
הלכה. Halacha. It's not a gap, it's a statement that there's no
concept of that. But anyway, but this one approach is to say
that דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina D'Malchusa Dina only sort of fills in
gaps. Now according to that approach, by the way, that could be
very nice here because you could say the fact that some land
could be left ownerless, leave A and not yet get to B
is a gap, it's like a problem, right? That a normal system
shouldn't work that way. And maybe that's like an opportune place for
הלכה Halacha to come in and to fill the—not הלכה, Halacha, דינא
דמלכותא Dina D'Malchusa to come in and to fill that gap. Okay,
but that doesn't resolve it because שמואל here is saying you do
have that gap even though you have דינא דמלכותא. Dina D'Malchusa. So
another possibility that comes up
is one of the גאונים Geonim and this focuses on this phrase
דינא דמלכותא. Dina D'Malchusa. Because the primary סוגיא sugya of דינא דמלכותא
Dina D'Malchusa is in בבא קמא Bava Kamma where it's applied to
the idea of the government taking taxes. And if they take your
property in taxes and then they use your property to build roads
and to build bridges, I don't have to feel like, oh I'm
stealing from Charlie because that's Charlie's wood that they used to build
that bridge and the government is a גנב ganav and whatever. No,
דינא דמלכותא דינא. Dina D'Malchusa Dina. The government has a right to
levy taxes and etc. So therefore there's a position of the גאונים
Geonim that says דינא דמלכותא דינא Dina D'Malchusa Dina only applies to
what is known I believe in law as
public law, which means—I think that's the word for it—which means it's
law that governs the relationship between the citizens and the government. So
the law that governs your obligations to the government and what the
government's rights to you and your
property, that is binding. The law that governs the relationship between individuals,
between citizens, standard civil law, that's not דינא דמלכותא, Dina D'Malchusa, that's
like הלכה Halacha would apply. Which makes a lot of sense, right?
Because if you think about it, we have all of the laws
of, you know, נזיקין Nezikin and civil law and חושן משפט Choshen
Mishpat which are about interpersonal laws. We don't have any laws that
define our relationship to the government, right?
Where's the הלכה? Halacha? Show me the מסכת Masechet that deals with
the laws that define our relationship to the government. So that is
דינא דמלכותא דינא. Dina D'Malchusa Dina. You're living in a secular government,
their laws, they define your obligations to them and their rights to
you. But the interpersonal obligations, those are still defined by הלכה. Halacha.
That's the position of the גאונים Geonim and that actually resolves this
גמרא Gemara very well. Right? Because yes, דינא דמלכותא דינא, Dina D'Malchusa
Dina, but between you and the non-Jew and when that קנין kinyan
transfers, that goes by הלכה Halacha and that leaves this opening. Yes.
Until 1948
because of the State of Israel. Right.
דינא דמלכותא Dina D'Malchusa becomes
the State of Israel, right?
And it's like because of the way we've lived for thousands of
years, we're missing exactly all these הלכות halachot of how to not
just be, you know, you and me and our property or whatever,
but how to establish a whole exactly.
I really appreciate you saying that. That's exactly true. The reason there
are no הלכות halachot that govern our relationship because the state had
always been, you know, non-Jewish. And the same way there are no
laws about that, there are no laws about how does a Jewish
government run. How does it—and not just like the technical things about
voting, like those big questions, how do you run a police force?
And how do you do all those right—all those
big—and that's why for a lot of people, you know, when the
founding of the State of Israel was very exciting, we're going to
develop a new הלכה, halacha, הלכה halacha that takes communal national responsibility
and so on. You know, but that—and that's how some people are
still—it still needs to be done, absolutely.
Yeah, interesting thing here.
רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot lived in a place where there was
no such thing really as private land ownership outside towns and cities
and Jews were completely outside the feudal system almost. So there they
would not have any reality on things like selling land. Right, that's
true. But in בבל, Bavel, which part Persian Empire, they did have
privately owned land. Aha. So it's—so that's why we're getting all these
Babylonian Amoraic.
Interesting, interesting. So I want to just read one last thing though
because there's a great רשב"ם Rashbam that sort of talks about—who was
it that says—who was it that developed the whole theory of the
implicit consent of the governed? Was that Rousseau? Was that—I'm forgetting my
enlightenment thinkers. Anyway, take a look here at שמואל—at the רשב"ם that
says מי אמר שמואל הכי? Mi amar Shmuel hachi? It is one,
two, three, four, five—oh my god—it's about fifteen lines before the lines
get the widest from the bottom of the middle-sized lines, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine, ten. Yeah about fifteen. The line starts with
the word לחזור זה בזה. lachzor ze baze. So he says, מי
אמר שמואל הכי דקני ליה שני לארעא דעובדי כוכבים. Mi amar Shmuel
hachi dekani lei sheini le'ara d'ovdei kochavim. And Shmuel
דינא דמלכותא דינא *dina demalchuta dina*. Line starts with the word דינא
*dina*. כל מכסין וארנונות *kol michsin ve'arnonot*, so that's taxes, that's the
sort of the law of your relationship to the government, ומנהגות של
משפטי מלכים שהרגילו להנהיג במלכותם *uminhagot shel mishpetei melachim shehergilu lehanhig bemalchutam*.
Now, that still sounds very much like this public law, not necessarily
interpersonal. Anyway, דינא הוא *dina hu* שכל בני המלכות מקבלים עליהם מרצונם
חוקי המלך ומשפטיו *shekol bnei hamalchut mekablim aleihem
mirtsonam chukei hamelech umishpatav*. ואי לכך דין גמור הוא ואין למחזיק בממון
חברו על פי חוק המלך הנהוג בעיר משום גזל *ve'ilachach din gamur
hu ve'ein lemachzik bemamon chaveiro al pi chok hamelech hanehug ba'ir mishum
gezel*. Okay, so the key phrase was that he tried to give
an explanation, and this is also a fascinating thing if you read
the ראשונים *rishonim* of דינא דמלכותא דינא *dina demalchuta dina*. For some
of them, it becomes an opportunity to put forth a political theory.
What is the logic? Why is the law of the government the
law? And that's like sort of says, well, what's my political theory?
Why does the government have right to make law on its citizens?
So the רשב"ם *Rashbam*'s political theory is basically because an implicit consent
of the governed. Right, it's very interesting. Others have different ideas like,
oh, because the ר"ן *Ran*'s idea is, and since we mentioned ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, we'll mention this and then we'll end, the ר"ן
*Ran*'s idea is, and this reflects a feudal system, the king owns
the land. Yeah. And since the king owns the land and he's
letting you stay on the land, he gets a right to tell
you what are the rules. Okay, so that very much reflects a
feudal system where it's basically all the king's land. So some want
to say, oh, so basically then the ר"ן *Ran* says, oh, so
this wouldn't apply in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, because in ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael*, every Jew has a right to their plot of land.
It's not fundamentally the king's land. Right. So then it becomes an
interesting question when the פוסקים *poskim* want to explain in modern-day Israel
what is the theory on which the, you know, that we can
build halachically an idea of a state. Right? You want to build
it on the concept of the תורה *Torah* of מלך *melech* and
say this is like a modern instantiation of the idea of king?
Or if some want to say, no, we'll treat it just like
any secular state, דינא דמלכותא דינא *dina demalchuta dina*, you know, just
like we had to follow the rules in, you know, in England
and in France, we have to follow the rules in Israel. Right.
So that's a very non-Zionist approach to it. Right. But then the
idea is, oh, and if that's the case, we don't have to
follow the rules because the ר"ן *Ran* says it's only because the
king owns the land. So this actually can become the basis for
those that want to say that we don't have to follow the
rules of the State of Israel. It's like it's no better than
any secular government and it's actually worse than a secular government because
fundamentally it's not this idea that the king owns the land. So
this becomes very interesting as, a, an opportunity for ראשונים *rishonim* to
discuss political theory, and, b, for this question of how do we
conceptualize halachically that sense of the authority of the State of Israel.
So here you're saying that
this theory here in the רשב"ם *Rashbam* of the consent of the
governed as the basis of the authority of the government 500 years
before Hume, Locke.
Yeah. I mean, I assume that that one idea of consent of
the governed was not, I mean,
it's an ancient idea.
Yeah, I don't, right, I mean, I assume it didn't take like,
you know, a Hume or Locke to come up with, I mean,
I assume it had more to do with the development of Enlightenment,
etc. Exactly,
exactly. But it is interesting to see this.
He's saying Wikipedia's idea of first mentioned.
Of the consent of the governed, first mentioned 1433 by whom? Nicholas
of Cusa.
Oh, look at that.
So the רשב"ם *Rashbam* beat him by a few 200 years or
something. Yeah.
Maybe they were talking about... Yeah, exactly.
You
have to go ahead and edit that page on Wikipedia. That you're
able to do.